So today I'm going to talk to you
اليوم سوف أتحدث
about the rise of collaborative consumption.
حول زيادة نسب الاستهلاك التعاوني.
I'm going to explain what it is
وسوف اشرح ماهو
and try and convince you -- in just 15 minutes --
وأحاول اقناعكم -- في 15 دقيقة فقط --
that this isn't a flimsy idea,
أن هذه ليست فكرة واهية،
or a short-term trend,
أو إتجاه قصير المدى،
but a powerful cultural and economic force
ولكن قوة ثقافية واقتصادية كبيرة،
reinventing not just what we consume,
إعادة اختراع، ليس فقط ما نستهلكه،
but how we consume.
ولكن كيف نستهلكه.
Now I'm going to start with a deceptively simple example.
الآن انا سأبدء مع مثال يبدو بسيطاً.
Hands up -- how many of you
ارفعوا ايديكم -- من منكم
have books, CDs, DVDs, or videos
لديه كتب واقراص واقلام
lying around your house
موجودة بمنازلكم
that you probably won't use again,
علي الأغلب لن تستخدموها مرة أخري،
but you can't quite bring yourself to throw away?
لكن لاتستطيعون رميها؟
Can't see all the hands,
لا استطيع رؤية كل الأيدي،
but it looks like all of you, right?
لكن علي مايبدو انكم كلكم معي.
On our shelves at home,
في رفوف منازلنا،
we have a box set of the DVD series "24,"
نحن لدينا مجموعة من حلقات مسلسل "24" --
season six to be precise.
الموسم السادس على وجه الدقة.
I think it was bought for us around three years ago for a Christmas present.
وأعتقد أنه كان قد إهدي لنا منذ ثلاث سنوات كهدية عيد الميلاد.
Now my husband, Chris, and I
الان انا وزوجي كريس
love this show.
نحب هذا المسلسل.
But let's face it, when you've watched it once maybe, or twice,
ولكن دعونا نواجه الأمر ، عندما تشاهده مرة واحدة -- ربما، أو مرتين --
you don't really want to watch it again,
لا تريد حقا في مشاهدته مرة أخرى،
because you know how Jack Bauer is going to defeat the terrorists.
لأنك تعرف كيف أن جاك باور سيهزم الارهابيين.
So there it sits on our shelves
لذا فهو هناك علي رفوفنا
obsolete to us,
متقادم بالنسبة لنا ،
but with immediate latent value to someone else.
ولكن ذو قيمة كامنة فورية لشخص آخر.
Now before we go on, I have a confession to make.
الأن وقبل ان استرسل، لدي اعتراف.
I lived in New York for 10 years,
انا عشت في نيويورك لعشر سنوات،
and I am a big fan of "Sex and the City."
وانا معجبة كبيرة بفيلم "الجنس والمدينة".
Now I'd love to watch the first movie again
الآن أحب مشاهدة الجزء الأول مرة اخري
as sort of a warm-up to the sequel coming out next week.
كإحماء قبل مشاهدة الجزء الثاني الذي سيعرض الأسبوع المقبل.
So how easily could I swap
فكيف يمكن بسهولة أنا اقوم بمبادلة
our unwanted copy of "24"
نسختنا غير المرغوب فيها من "24"
for a wanted copy of "Sex and the City?"
بالنسخة المرغوبة من "الجنس والمدينة"؟
Now you may have noticed
ويمكن الملاحظة الان
there's a new sector emerging called swap-trading.
ان هناك قطاع جديدا يظهر يسمي تجارة المقايضة.
Now the easiest analogy for swap-trading
اسهل صورة لتجارة المقايضة هي
is like an online dating service
مثل انظمة المواعدة علي الانترنت
for all your unwanted media.
لكل وسائطك (أفلام - مسلسلات) غير المرغوب فيها
What it does is use the Internet
ما تفعله هو استخدام الانترنت
to create an infinite marketplace
لإنشاء سوق لانهائي
to match person A's "haves"
ليطابق ما يملكه الشخص أ
with person C's "wants,"
مع مايريده الشخص ب،
whatever they may be.
اي ما يكون ذلك.
The other week, I went on one of these sites,
الاسبوع الماضي، ذهبت لاحدي هذه المواقع،
appropriately called Swaptree,
يسمي سواب تري.
and there were over 59,300 items
وكان هناك اكثر من 59300 عنصر
that I could instantly swap
يمكنني مبادلته في الحال
for my copy of "24."
بنسخة مسلسل "24" خاصتي.
Lo and behold,
لاحظوا معي،
there in Reseda, CA was Rondoron
هناك في ريسيدا، كاليفورنيا كان روندورن
who wanted swap his or her
الذي أراد أو أرادت مبادلة
"like new" copy of "Sex and the City"
نسخة "مثل الجديدة " من "الجنس والمدينة"
for my copy of "24."
مقابل نسختي من "24".
So in other words, what's happening here
بعبارة اخري ان مايجري هنا
is that Swaptree
ان سوابتري
solves my carrying company's sugar rush problem,
يحل مشكلة حمل سكر الشركة الخاصة بي
a problem the economists call "the coincidence of wants,"
مشكلة يطلق عليها الاقتصاديون "تصادف الأحتياجات"
in approximately 60 seconds.
في 60 ثانية تقريباً.
What's even more amazing is it will print out a postage label on the spot,
والمدهش أكثر هو أنه سوف يطبع طابع شراء على الفور،
because it knows the way of the item.
لأنه يعرف الوزن الخاص بالعنصر.
Now there are layers of technical wonder
الآن هناك طبقات من عجب التقنية
behind sites such as Swaptree,
وراء مواقع مثل سواب تري,
but that's not my interest,
ولكن هذا ليس اهتمامي،
and nor is swap trading, per se.
ولا تجارة المقايضة في حد ذاتها.
My passion, and what I've spent the last few years
شغفي والذي قضيت فيه سنواتي الأخيرة
dedicated to researching,
متفرغة للبحث،
is the collaborative behaviors and trust-mechanics
هي السلوكيات التعاونية و آليات الثقة
inherent in these systems.
المتأصلة في هذه النظم.
When you think about it,
عندما تفكر في ذلك،
it would have seemed like a crazy idea, even a few years ago,
ربما بدت مثل فكرة مجنونة، حتى سنوات قليلة مضت ،
that I would swap my stuff with a total stranger
أن أبادل أشيائي مع شخص غريب
whose real name I didn't know
اسمه الحقيقي لم أكن أعرفه
and without any money changing hands.
ودون أي تبادل للمال.
Yet 99 percent of trades on Swaptree
لكن معظم التبادلات في ذلك الموقع 99 منها
happen successfully,
يحدث بنجاح.
and the one percent that receive a negative rating,
والواحد في المئة منها الذي يحصل على التصويت السلبي،
it's for relatively minor reasons,
فلأسباب بسيطة نسبيا،
like the item didn't arrive on time.
مثل عدم الوصول الوقت المحدد.
So what's happening here?
فماذا يحدث هنا؟
An extremely powerful dynamic
ديناميكية قوية للغاية
that has huge commercial and cultural implications
لها آثارها الضخمة التجارية والثقافية
is at play.
هي في الملعب.
Namely, that technology
وهي أن التكنولوجيا
is enabling
هي تمكين
trust between strangers.
الثقة بين الغرباء.
We now live in a global village
نحن الآن نعيش في قرية عالمية
where we can mimic the ties
حيث يمكننا محاكاة العلاقات
that used to happen face to face,
التي كانت تحدث وجها لوجه،
but on a scale and in ways
ولكن على نطاق وبطرق
that have never been possible before.
لم تكن ممكنة من قبل.
So what's actually happening
ما يحدث فعلا هو ان
is that social networks and real-time technologies
الشبكات الاجتماعية والتكنولوجيات الانية
are taking us back.
تاخذنا للوراء.
We're bartering, trading,
نحن نقايض، نتاجر،
swapping, sharing,
نبادل، نشارك،
but they're being reinvented
لكن يتم إعادة إبتكارهم
into dynamic and appealing forms.
في أشكال ديناميكية وجذابة.
What I find fascinating
ما اجده مثيرا للدهشة ورائعا
is that we've actually wired our world to share,
هو اننا مرتبطون بالمشاركة
whether that's our neighborhood, our school,
سواء في الحي او المدرسة،
our office, or our Facebook network,
المكتب او شبكة الفيسبوك الخاصة بنا.
and that's creating an economy
وهذا يصنع اقتصاد
of "what's mine is yours."
ماهو لي فهو لك.
From the mighty eBay,
من موقع اي بي الجبار،
the grandfather of exchange marketplaces,
جد اسواق التبادل،
to car-sharing companies such as GoGet,
لشركات مشاركة السيارات مثل جوجيت،
where you pay a monthly fee to rent cars by the hour,
حيث يمكنك دفع رسم شهري لتأجير السيارات بنظام الساعة،
to social lending platforms such as Zopa,
إلى منصات الإقراض الاجتماعية مثل زوبا،
that will take anyone in this audience
التي سوف تأخذ أي شخص في هذا الجمهور
with 100 dollars to lend,
لديه 100 دولار ليقرضها،
and match them with a borrower anywhere in the world,
ومطابقتها مع المقترض في أي مكان في العالم،
we're sharing and collaborating again
نحن تبادل ونتعاون مرة أخرى
in ways that I believe
بالطرق التي أعتقد
are more hip than hippie.
عصرية أكثر منها هيبية.
I call this "groundswell collaborative consumption."
مااسميه فيض الاستهلاك التعاوني.
Now before I dig into the different systems
الأن قبل أن أدلف الي النظم المختلفة
of collaborative consumption,
من الاستهلاك التعاوني،
I'd like to try and answer the question
اود الاجابة علي سؤال
that every author rightfully gets asked,
يٌسأله كل كاتب بحق،
which is, where did this idea come from?
وهو من اين اتت هذه الفكرة.
Now I'd like to say I woke up one morning
الآن أود أن أقول أنني استيقظت في صباح أحد الأيام
and said, "I'm going to write about collaborative consumption,"
وقلت "اني سوف أكتب عن الاستهلاك التعاوني."
but actually it was a complicated web
ولكن الحقيقة انها كانت شبكة معقدة
of seemingly disconnected ideas.
من الافكار المتقطعة.
Over the next minute,
علي مدار الدقيقة القادمة،
you're going to see a bit like a conceptual fireworks display
سترون ما يشبه قليلا عرض الالعاب النارية الخيالي
of all the dots that went on in my head.
من كل النقاط التي دارت في رأسي.
The first thing I began to notice:
أول شيء بدأت ألاحظه :
how many big concepts were emerging --
هو كم من المفاهيم الكبري بدأت تنشأ --
from the wisdom of crowds to smart mobs --
من حكمة الحشود الي ذكاء الغوغاء --
around how ridiculously easy it is
و كم كان ذلك سهلاً بصورة غريبة
to form groups for a purpose.
أن تٌشكل مجموعات لغرض.
And linked to this crowd mania
ومرتبطاً بهذا الهوس الجماعي
were examples all around the world --
كانت الأمثلة في جميع أنحاء العالم --
from the election of a president
من انتخاب رئيس
to the infamous Wikipedia, and everything in between --
لويكيبيديا الشائنة، و كل شيء بين ذلك --
on what the power of numbers could achieve.
علي مايمكن أن تحققه قوة الاعداد.
Now, you know when you learn a new word,
الآن، كما تعلمون عندما تتعلم كلمة جديدة،
and then you start to see that word everywhere?
ثم تبدأ في رؤية تلك الكلمة في كل مكان؟
That's what happened to me
هذا ما حدث لي
when I noticed that we are moving
عندما لاحظت أننا نتحرك
from passive consumers
من مستهلكين سلبيين
to creators,
لمبدعين،
to highly enabled collaborators.
لمشاركين ممكنين للغاية.
What's happening
ماذا يحدث
is the Internet is removing the middleman,
هو ان الإنترنت يحذف الوسيط،
so that anyone from a T-shirt designer
بحيث يمكن لأي شخص من مصمم تي شيرت
to a knitter
إلى العاقد
can make a living selling peer-to-peer.
يمكن ان يكسب من البيع للمستهلك مباشرة.
And the ubiquitous force
والقوة المنتشرة في كل مكان
of this peer-to-peer revolution
لهذا التطور في علاقات الند-للند
means that sharing is happening at phenomenal rates.
تعني أن التشارك يحدث بمعدلات هائلة.
I mean, it's amazing to think
أعني، إنه لأمر مدهش أن نفكر
that, in every single minute of this speech,
أنه في كل دقيقة واحدة من هذا الخطاب ،
25 hours
25 ساعة
of YouTube video will be loaded.
سيتم تحميلها في يوتيوب.
Now what I find fascinating about these examples
الآن ما أجده رائعاً في هذه الأمثلة
is how they're actually tapping into
هوكيف انهم في الواقع يستفيدون
our primate instincts.
من غرائزنا الأساسية.
I mean, we're monkeys,
يعني، أننا قرود،
and we're born and bred to share and cooperate.
ونحن نولد وننشأ للمشاركة والتعاون.
And we were doing so for thousands of years,
وكنا نفعل ذلك منذ آلاف السنين،
whether it's when we hunted in packs,
سواء عندما كنا نصيد في جماعات،
or farmed in cooperatives,
او مارسنا الزراعة بالتعاون،
before this big system called hyper-consumption came along
قبل قدوم هذا النظام الجديد المدعو الاستهلاك المفرط
and we built these fences
وقمنا ببناء هذه الأسوار
and created out own little fiefdoms.
وصنعنا اقطاعياتنا الخاصة.
But things are changing,
لكن الاشياء تتغير،
and one of the reasons why
وأحد الأسباب هو
is the digital natives, or Gen-Y.
السكان الرقميين أوالجيل واي.
They're growing up sharing --
انهن نشأوا وهم يتشاركون --
files, video games, knowledge.
الملفات، وألعاب الفيديو، والمعرفة؛
It's second nature to them.
انها طبيعة ثانية لهم.
So we, the millennials -- I am just a millennial --
حتى نحن ، جيل الألفية -- أنا من جيل الالفية ايضا --
are like foot soldiers,
مثل جنود المشاة،
moving us from a culture of "me" to a culture of "we."
ننتقل من ثقافة أنا ، إلى ثقافة نحن.
The reason why it's happening so fast
السبب أنه يحدث بسرعة جداً
is because of mobile collaboration.
هو بسبب التعاون بتقنيات الموبايل.
We now live in a connected age
نحن نعيش الآن في عصر الاتصال
where we can locate anyone, anytime, in real-time,
حيث يمكننا تحديد مكان أي شخص، في أي وقت، في الوقت الحقيقي،
from a small device in our hands.
من جهاز صغير في أيدينا.
All of this was going through my head
كل ذلك كان يمر برأسي
towards the end of 2008,
في أواخر عام 2008،
when, of course, the great financial crash happened.
عندما، بالطبع، وقع حادثة مالية كبيرة.
Thomas Friedman is one of my favorite New York Times columnists,
توماس فريدمان هو واحد من كتاب الأعمدة المفضلين لي بالنيويورك تايمز،
and he poignantly commented
وعلق بمرارة
that 2008 is when we hit a wall,
أن عام 2008 هو عندما اصطدمنا بالحائط
when Mother Nature and the market
عندما قالت الطبيعة الأم والسوق
both said, "No more."
معاً "كفي"
Now we rationally know
نحن الان نعرف عقليا
that an economy built on hyper-consumption
ان الاقتصاد المبني علي الاستهلاك المفرط
is a Ponzi scheme. It's a house of cards.
هو مخطط بونزي، بل أوهن من بيت العنكبوت.
Yet, it's hard for us to individually know what to do.
ومع ذلك ، فإنه من الصعب بالنسبة لنا أن نعرف ما يجب القيام به بشكل فردي.
So all of this is a lot of twittering, right?
لذلك كل هذا هو الكثير من إستخدام التويتر، أليس كذلك؟
Well it was a lot of noise and complexity in my head,
حسناً قد كان هناك الكثير من الضجيج والتعقيد في رأسي،
until actually I realized it was happening
حتى أدركت انه في الواقع ماكان يحدث
because of four key drivers.
بسبب اربعة اشياء اساسية
One, a renewed belief in the importance of community,
الأول، وهو الاعتقاد المتجدد في أهمية المجتمع،
and a very redefinition of what friend and neighbor really means.
وإعادة تعريف ماذا يعني الصديق والجار حقا.
A torrent of peer-to-peer social networks
برامج التورنت والشبكات الاجتماعية
and real-time technologies,
والتكنولوجيا الأنية،
fundamentally changing the way we behave.
تغير جذرياً الطريقة التي نتصرف بها.
Three, pressing unresolved environmental concerns.
ثالثاً، الاهتمامات البيئية الملحة التي لم تحل.
And four, a global recession
ورابعاً ،الكساد العالمي
that has fundamentally shocked
الذي هز جذريا
consumer behaviors.
سلوكيات المستهلك.
These four drivers
هذه العوامل الأربعة
are fusing together
تنصهر معا
and creating the big shift --
وتخلق التحول الكبير --
away from the 20th century,
بعيدا عن القرن 20،
defined by hyper-consumption,
يحددها الاستهلاك المفرط،
towards the 21st century,
نحو القرن 21،
defined by collaborative consumption.
يٌعرفها الاستهلاك التعاوني.
I generally believe we're at an inflection point
وأعتقد عموما أننا عند نقطة انعطاف
where the sharing behaviors --
حيث سلوكيات المشاركة --
through sites such as Flickr and Twitter
من خلال مواقع مثل فليكر وتويتر
that are becoming second nature online --
التي أصبحت الطبيعة الثانية على الانترنت --
are being applied to offline areas of our everyday lives.
يجري تطبيقها على مجالات حياتنا اليومية.
From morning commutes to the way fashion is designed
من الأنتقال الصباحي إلي طريقة تصميم الموضة
to the way we grow food,
إلي طريقة زراعة المحاصيل الغذائية،
we are consuming and collaborating once again.
نحن نستهلك ونتعاون مرة اخري
So my co-author, Roo Rogers, and I
لذلك فالكاتب المشارك معي، روو روجرز، وانا
have actually gathered thousands of examples
جمعنا في الواقع الآلاف من الأمثلة
from all around the world of collaborative consumption.
من جميع أنحاء العالم علي الاستهلاك التعاوني.
And although they vary enormously
وعلى الرغم من أنها تختلف اختلافا كبيرا
in scale, maturity and purpose,
من حيث النضج في الحجم والغرض،
when we dived into them,
وعندما غصنا في تفاصيلها،
we realized that they could actually be organized into three clear systems.
وأدركنا أنه يمكن فعلا أن ننقسم إلى ثلاثة أنظمة واضحة.
The first is redistribution markets.
الأول هو أسواق إعادة التوزيع.
Redistribution markets, just like Swaptree,
أسواق إعادة التوزيع -- تماما مثل سواب تري --
are when you take a used, or pre-owned, item
هي عندما تاخذ العناصر المستخدمة او المملوكة لك
and move it from where it's not needed
وتنقلها من حيث لا حاجة إليها
to somewhere, or someone, where it is.
إلى مكان ما، أو شخص ما، حيث هناك حاجة لها.
They're increasingly thought of as the fifth 'R' --
يتم التفكير فيهم بطريقة متزايدة كـخمسة "R" --
reduce, reuse, recycle, repair
التقليل، اعادة الاستخدام، اعادة التدوير، الصيانة
and redistribute --
واعادة التوزيع --
because they stretch the life cycle of a product
لأنها تمدد دورة حياة المنتج
and thereby reduce waste.
وبالتالي تقلل النفايات.
The second is collaborative lifestyles.
والثاني هو نمط الحياة التعاوني.
This is the sharing of resources
هذا هو التشارك وموارد
of things like money, skills and time.
من أشياء مثل المهارات ، والمال والوقت.
I bet, in a couple of years,
أراهن، أنه في بضع سنوات،
that phrases like "coworking"
أن عبارات مثل المشاركة في العمل
and "couchsurfing" and "time banks"
وتبادل الإستضافة وبنوك الوقت
are going to become a part of everyday vernacular.
سوف تصبح جزءا من العامية اليومية.
One of my favorite examples of collaborative lifestyles
واحد من الأمثلة المفضلة لدي لأنماط الحياة التعاونية
is called Landshare.
تسمي مشاركة الارض.
It's a scheme in the U.K.
إنه مخطط في بريطانيا.
that matches Mr. Jones,
يطابق السيد جونز،
with some spare space in his back garden,
مع بعض المساحة الخالية في حديقته الخلفية،
with Mrs. Smith, a would-be grower.
مع السيدة سميث، التي ترغب أن تكون مزارعة.
Together they grow their own food.
معا فإنهم يزرعون المحاصيل الغذائية الخاصة بهم.
It's one of those ideas that's so simple, yet brilliant,
انها واحدة من هذه الأفكار التي في غاية البساطة ، ومع ذلك رائعة،
you wonder why it's never been done before.
تجعلك تتساءل لماذا لم نقم بها من قبل.
Now, the third system
الآن النظام الثالث
is product-service systems.
هو نظم خدمة المنتج
This is where you pay for the benefit of the product --
حيث تدفع مقابل الاستفادة من المنتج --
what it does for you --
وماذا تفعل من أجلك --
without needing to own the product outright.
بدون الحاجة لملكية المنتج.
This idea is particularly powerful
الفكرة قوية فعلا
for things that have
للأشياء التي لها
high-idling capacity.
طاقة غير مستخدمة عالية.
And that can be anything from baby goods
ويمكن أن يكون هذا أي شيء من سلع الطفل
to fashions to --
الي الازياء مرورا بـ --
how many of you have a power drill,
من منكم لديه مثقاب كهربائي؟
own a power drill? Right.
تملكوه؟ صحيح.
That power drill will be used around 12 to 13 minutes
وهذه الاداة نستخدمها حوالي 12 -13 دقيقة
in its entire lifetime.
في كل حياتها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's kind of ridiculous, right?
انها نوع من السخف، أليس كذلك؟
Because what you need is the hole, not the drill.
لأن ما تحتاجه هو الثقب، وليس المثقاب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So why don't you rent the drill,
فلماذا لا يتم تأجير المثقاب،
or, even better, rent out your own drill to other people
أو، وحتى أفضل، تأجير المثقاب الخاص بك لأشخاص آخرين
and make some money from it?
وكسب بعض المال من ذلك؟
These three systems are coming together,
هذه الأنظمة الثلاثة معا،
allowing people to share resources
لتسمح للناس بتشارك الموارد
without sacrificing their lifestyles,
دون التضحية بأنماط حياتهم،
or their cherished personal freedoms.
أو حرياتهم الشخصية العزيزة.
I'm not asking people
أنا لا أطالب الناس
to share nicely in the sandpit.
ان تتشارك احواض الرمال.
So I want to just give you an example
لذلك أريد أن أعطيكم مثالا
of how powerful collaborative consumption can be
عن كيفية طريقة استهلاك تعاوني قوية يمكن
to change behaviors.
أن نغير السلوكيات.
The average car
السيارة المتوسطة
costs 8,000 dollars a year to run.
تكلف 8000 دولار في السنة لتعمل.
Yet, that car sits idle
ومع ذلك تظل بلا إستخدام
for 23 hours a day.
لـ 23 ساعة في اليوم.
So when you consider these two facts,
لذا عندما تفكر في هاتين الحقيقتين،
it starts to make a little less sense
يصبح الأمر أقل معقولية
that we have to own one outright.
أن نتملك سيارة.
So this is where car-sharing companies
لذا هنا حيث تأتي شركات مشاركة السيارات
such as Zipcar and GoGet come in.
مثل زيباكار و جوجت.
In 2009,
في 2009،
Zipcar took 250 participants
زيكبار اخذت 250 مشاركا
from across 13 cities --
من 13 مدينة --
and they're all self-confessed car addicts
وكلهم من مهووسي السيارات بإعترافهم
and car-sharing rookies --
والمبتدئين في مجال تشارك السيارات --
and got them to surrender their keys for a month.
وجعلتهم يتخلوا عن مفاتيحهم لمدة شهر.
Instead, these people had to walk,
وبدلا منها ،إضطر هؤلاء القوم أن يسيروا
bike, take the train,
ويستخدمو الدراجة والقطار،
or other forms of public transport.
أوالأشكال الاخري من وسائل النقل.
They could only use their Zipcar membership
ويمكنهم فقط إستخدام اشتراكهم في شركة زيكبار
when absolutely necessary.
عندما يكونوا في حاجة ملحة.
The results of this challenge after just one month
والنتيجة بعد شهر واحد.
was staggering.
كانت مذهلة.
It's amazing that 413 lbs were lost
من المدهش أن 413 باوندا تم فقدانها
just from the extra exercise.
فقط من التمرين الزائد.
But my favorite statistic
لكن افضل احصائية بالنسبة لي
is that 100
هي ان 100
out of the 250 participants
من ال 250 شخصا المشاركين
did not want their keys back.
لم يريدوا استرجاع مفاتيحهم.
In other words, the car addicts
بمعني اخر ان مهووسي السيارات
had lost their urge to own.
فقدوا حاجتهم للتملك
Now products-service systems have been around for years.
الأن نظم خدمة المنتجات موجودة منذ سنوات.
Just think of libraries and laundrettes.
فقط فكروا في المكتبات والمغاسل.
But I think they're entering a new age,
لكن اعتقد انها تدخل في عصر جديد،
because technology makes sharing
لأن التكنولوجيا تجعل المشاركة
frictionless and fun.
بلا مجهود وممتع.
There's a great quote that was written in the New York Times
هناك كلمة رائعة كتبت في صحيفة نيويورك تايمز
that said, "Sharing is to ownership
قيل فيها، "المشاركة بالنسبة للملكية
what the iPod is to the 8-track,
مثل iPod بالنسبة للشرائط من نوع - tracks 8
what solar power is to the coal mine."
أوالطاقة الشمسية بالنسبة لمناجم الفحم."
I believe also, our generation,
وأعتقد أيضا، ان جيلنا،
our relationship to satisfying what we want
علاقتنا بإشباع ما نريد
is far less tangible
ملموسة بشكل أقل بكثير
than any other previous generation.
من اي جيل اخر.
I don't want the DVD; I want the movie it carries.
انا لا أريد دي في دي، اريد الفيلم.
I don't want a clunky answering machine;
انا لا اريد ماكينة الرد الالي،
I want the message it saves.
انا اريد منها الرسالة التي تحفظها.
I don't want a CD; I want the music it plays.
انا لا اريد الاسطوانة، اريد الاغاني التي تحويها.
In other words, I don't want stuff;
بكلمة اخري، انا لا اريد الاشياء،
I want the needs or experiences it fulfills.
اريد الحاجات والتجارب التي تشبعها.
This is fueling a massive shift
هذا يغذي هذا تحول هائل
from where usage trumps possessions --
من حيث أن الإستخدام يتفوق علي الملكية --
or as Kevin Kelly, the editor of Wired magazine, puts it,
او كما قال كيفن كيلي، محرر مجلة "Wired"،
"where access is better than ownership."
"ان الإستخدام افضل من الامتلاك"
Now as our possessions
الأن كما هو الحال ممتلكاتنا
dematerialize into the cloud,
تختفي في السحاب،
a blurry line is appearing
هنالك خط ضبابي يظهر
between what's mine, what's yours,
بين ما هو لي وما هو لكم،
and what's ours.
وما هو لنا.
I want to give you one example
اود ان اعطيكم مثالا
that shows how fast this evolution is happening.
يظهر مدى سرعة حدوث هذا التطور.
This represents an eight-year time span.
هذا يمثل فترة حوالي 8 سنوات.
We've gone from traditional car-ownership
تحولنا من الامتلاك التقليدي للسيارات
to car-sharing companies, such as Zipcar and GoGet,
إلي شركات مشاركة السيارات -- مثل زيبكار و جو جت --
to ride-sharing platforms that match rides
الي مواقع مشاركة المركبات التي تقابل بين المركبات
to the newest entry, which is peer-to-peer car rental,
إلي العنصر الأحدث، وهو نظام تأجير السيارات من شخص الي شخص،
where you can actually make money
حيث يمكننا فعلا جني المال
out of renting that car that sits idle for 23 hours a day
من إيجار السيارة القابعة بلا حركة لـ23 ساعة في اليوم
to your neighbor.
لجارك.
Now all of these systems
الان كل هذه الانظمة
require a degree of trust,
تتطلب درجة من الثقة،
and the cornerstone to this working
وحجر الزاوية لهذا العمل.
is reputation.
هو السمعة.
Now in the old consumer system,
الآن في النظام القديم للإستهلاك،
our reputation didn't matter so much,
سمعتنا لا تهم كثيرا،
because our credit history was far more important
لأن تاريخنا الإئتماني كان أكثر أهمية بكثير
that any kind of peer-to-peer review.
من أي نوع من مراجعة الند-للند.
But now with the Web, we leave a trail.
ولكن الآن مع الويب، نحن نترك أثر.
With every spammer we flag,
مع كل شخص مزعج نضع علامة عليه،
with every idea we post, comment we share,
مع كل فكرة ننشرها، تعليق نشارك به،
we're actually signaling how well we collaborate,
نحن في الحقيقة نرسل إشارة عن جودة تعاونونا،
and whether we can or can't be trusted.
وما إذا كان من الممكن الثقة بنا أم لا.
Let's go back to my first example,
لنعد الي مثالي الاول،
Swaptree.
سواب تري
I can see that Rondoron
استطيع ان اري ان روندرون
has completed 553 trades
اكمل 553 عملية ناجحة
with a 100 percent success rate.
بمعدل نجاح 100 بالمئة.
In other words, I can trust him or her.
بمعني ، يمكنني الوثوق به أو بها.
Now mark my words,
أعيروني أنتباهكم،
it's only a matter of time
إنها مسألة وقت
before we're going to be able to perform a Google-like search
قبل أن نستطيع إجراء بحث مثل البحث علي جوجل
and see a cumulative picture
ونرى صورة تراكمية
of our reputation capital.
من رصيد السمعة الخاصة بنا.
And this reputation capital
وهذا الرصيد من السمعة
will determine our access to collaborative consumption.
سوف يحدد إمكانية دخولنا للإستهلاك التعاوني.
It's a new social currency, so to speak,
إنها عملة إجتماعية جديدة، ان جاز التعبير،
that could become as powerful as our credit rating.
يمكن أن تصبح قوية مثل تصنيفنا الإئتماني.
Now as a closing thought,
الأن كفكرة ختامية،
I believe we're actually in a period
أعتقد أننا في الواقع في فترة
where we're waking up
الاستيقاظ او الصحوة
from this humongous hangover
من الترنح العملاق
of emptiness and waste,
للفراغ، والنفايات،
and we're taking a leap
ونأخذ قفزة
to create a more sustainable system
لإنشاء نظام أكثر استدامة
built to serve our innate needs
يتم بنائه لخدمة احتياجاتنا الأساسية
for community and individual identity.
للمجتمع والهوية الفردية.
I believe it will be referred to
أعتقد أنه سيشار إليه
as a revolution, so to speak --
كثورة، إذا جاز التعبير --
when society, faced with great challenges,
عندما يواجه المجتمع تحديات كبيرة،
made a seismic shift
ليصنع تحولا مزلزلا
from individual getting and spending
من الحصول والانفاق الفردي
towards a rediscovery of collective good.
نحو إعادة اكتشاف الصالح العام.
I'm on a mission to make sharing cool.
أنا في مهمة لجعل التشارك جميل ومريح.
I'm on a mission to make sharing hip.
أنا في مهمة لجعل التشارك عصري.
Because I really believe
لاني حقاً أؤمن
it can disrupt outdated modes of business,
أنه يمكن أن يعطل وسائل عفا عليها الزمن لأداء الأعمال،
help us leapfrog
يساعدنا على تخطي
over wasteful forms of hyper-consumption
استهلاكنا المفرط المٌهدر
and teach us when enough really is enough.
ويعلمنا عندما نصل للكفاية الحقيقية.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)